If I can stand in for Master and protect this town,
如果我能代替主人守護這座城鎮
I'll do it.
那我願意守在這裡
With the encouragement of my companions,
在同伴的鼓勵下找回勇氣的我
I've decided to save Manicia and protect this town.
決定在拯救瑪妮西婭的同時
To realize these objectives,
為了實現這些夢想
I must successfully raid the labyrinth.
我一定要成功攻略迷宮
Just when I was going to prepare to establish a clan,
在那之後，我馬上準備建立戰團
I was summoned by the investigators of Avancia's labyrinth…
卻被阿凡錫亞迷宮的調查員傳喚
only to find out that those investigators were members of my former party.
只是沒想到那些調查員 竟然是過去的隊伍成員
So, let me reintroduce myself.
那麼，我再重新自我介紹一次
I'm Lilia.
我是莉莉亞
I believe this is the first time we've met since you were fired.
這是你被開除後第一次見面吧，路德
I'm the younger of the twins, Lily.
我是雙胞胎妹妹，莉莉
Although we're twins, our eye colors are different
我們是雙胞胎，但眼睛顏色不同
due to our unique constitution.
是特異體質的關係
They're really close.
靠得好近
Thank you for all your hard work.
之前辛苦各位了
I'm Shugor, the knight of the church.
我是教會的騎士，修格爾
I… I am Luna.
我是露娜
It's nice to meet you.
請多多指教
Well, let's discuss the details inside.
那麼，詳細內容就進來再說吧
Yo.
嗨
Long time no see, Rud.
好久不見了，路德
How dare you summon us!
真虧你敢叫我們過來
After everything you did to Rud!
之前明明對路德做了那麼過分的事
Thank you,
謝謝你
but I've put that behind me.
不過我已經不介意了
Kygras,
吉古拉斯
tell me why we're here.
請你告訴我理由
I'm sure you didn't call us here just to say hello.
你叫我們過來 應該不只是為了打招呼吧？
Yesterday,
就在昨天
we encountered a sentient guardian during our investigation.
我們在調查途中 遇到了擁有自我意識的守護者
A sentient guardian?
擁有自我意識的守護者？
Of all the labyrinth guardians we've fought up until now,
之前對戰過的迷宮守護者
even if capable of taking on human forms,
就算擁有人類的外型
were incapable of speech.
應該也無法進行對話才對
You've seen what a miserable state I'm in,
你也看到我這副慘樣了
so…
所以…
I'm just trying to finish the quest while slacking off.
我只是想打混摸魚，等任務完成啦
Don't complain. Just do it.
別囉哩囉嗦的，做就對了！
In short,
簡單來說
having you investigate the labyrinth in his place
讓你接替他進去調查
is this guy's way of apologizing.
就是這傢伙的道歉方式
Don't say that!
你這傢伙，別亂說！
What, are you shy?
幹嘛？你害羞了嗎？
I'm not!
我才沒有害羞！
Ugh, seriously.
真是的
To cure your sister,
為了給妹妹治病
don't you need the labyrinth's treasure?
你不是需要迷宮祕寶嗎？
You remember that?
原來你還記得啊？
I… know the reason
我…
I've been able to successfully raid
已經知道自己至今以來
the labyrinths up until now.
為何能順利戰鬥了
So, what's your decision?
所以你打算怎麼做？
Are you going to do it or not?
是要去調查，還是不去？
Please let me do it.
請讓我進去調查
In that case, I'll be borrowing Lilia and the others.
那麼我就暫時借走莉莉亞他們了
Rud,
路德
I'm sorry about everything.
之前真的很抱歉
Don't die.
你可不要死掉喔
Thanks.
謝謝你
I will defeat the guardian.
我一定會打倒守護者的
I didn't expect Kygras to say all of that.
沒想到那個吉古拉斯居然會這麼說
But it's great to have a full party.
不過能湊齊戰力真是太好了
Yes.
是啊
Let's raid Avancia's labyrinth.
我們開始攻略阿凡錫亞迷宮吧！
This is…
這是…
We'll be teleporting to the first floor from here.
我們要從這裡被傳送到迷宮第一層
Let's go.
那麼，我們走吧
I had no idea it would be so spacious inside the labyrinth.
沒想到那個入口裡面 居然有這麼寬闊的地方
You can even see the sun.
甚至還有太陽耶
Just a reminder, that sun won't move.
提醒一下，那個太陽不會動
Be careful not to let it distort your sense of time.
所以要小心，避免時間錯亂
As the space inside is warped,
因為迷宮裡的空間是扭曲的
many things that are impossible in reality can happen here.
所以發生超乎現實的現象 是稀鬆平常的事
The magic circle disappeared.
魔法陣消失了
Doesn't that mean we can't go back?
這樣不就回不去了嗎？
That's right.
是啊
If we want to go back, we'll have to find another magic circle.
要回去的話就得尋找新配置的魔法陣
But don't worry about it.
不過你不用擔心
Lily has a skill called Dungeon Walk.
因為莉莉有叫做“迷宮傳送”的技能
Normally,
一般的狀況下想往返各個樓層
you have to locate the randomly configured magic circles.
就必須尋找隨機配置的魔法陣
However, with Dungeon Walk,
不過只要有“迷宮傳送”
you can move freely between floors you've been to.
就可以任意往返曾經去過的樓層
DUNGEON WALK
是喔
But the skill only allows for a maximum of six.
但是能接受技能恩惠的
So, only six people can be teleported at the same time.
所以一次最多只能移動六個人
There are other spells similar to Dungeon Walk.
也有其他類似迷宮傳送的魔法
Nin, show it to Luna.
妮恩，你施展給露娜看看
Got it.
了解
This is an emergency escape spell.
這是緊急逃離用的魔法
Let me try it.
-我試試看 -什麼？
She learned it in an instant.
居然一瞬間就學會了
Impressive.
太厲害了
That was most likely the ability
剛才那招恐怕是動用了 戰鬥用人造人的能力吧
Three Chameleon Kongs approaching.
有三隻變色龍金剛在朝這邊前進
Lilia and Shugor, take the front.
莉莉亞和修格爾負責前衛
Nin and Lily will be in the rearguard. Handle support and healing.
妮恩和莉莉是後衛
Luna will move around and protect the party.
露娜負責四處移動，守護大家
And I, as always,
而我會跟平時一樣
will be the tank.
成為大家的盾！
Taunt!
挑釁！
Let's defeat them with this momentum!
-就以這股氣勢打倒牠們！ -好！
This party is good.
這支隊伍真不錯呢
This is where the guardian appeared last time.
之前守護者就是在這裡出現的
Not this time, though.
這次不在這裡呢
Fieldsauruses!
是菲爾多龍！
They are faster than the ones in other labyrinths.
移動速度比普通迷宮裡的還快
Is this the work of the guardian here?
是這裡的守護者搞的鬼嗎？
I'll handle these guys.
這些傢伙由我負責
You guys find the magic circle.
你們去找魔法陣！
Got it.
知道了
Taunt!
挑釁！
Remember to conserve strength for the guardian battle.
記得要保留力量跟守護者戰鬥
Found the magic circle.
找到魔法陣了！
Great. Let's progress.
很好，趕緊繼續前進
Good judgment.
很明智的判斷
Eighth floor.
第八層
Ninth floor.
第九層
Hurry up and come to me.
快點過來我這邊吧
The next floor is finally the tenth floor.
下一層終於就是第十層了
Everyone,
各位
thank you for going along with my selfish request.
謝謝你們願意配合我的任性行為
What's with it all of a sudden?
幹嘛突然這樣啊？
No need to be so polite.
不用這麼客氣啦
It's for your sister, right?
你是為了妹妹吧？
I understand how important your family is to you.
我能理解你重視家人的心情
That's right…
沒錯…
It's too soon to say "thank you."
現在說“謝謝”還太早了
Rud.
路德
This is where the challenge begins.
接下來才是重頭戲喔
Right.
好
Let's defeat the guardian together.
大家一起打倒守護者吧
It's a sea of grass.
一整片都是草原耶
That was
你們幾個
a splendid performance.
剛才的表現非常精彩喔
This guy is…
這傢伙就是…
I never expected such powerful adventurers.
沒想到居然會有 這麼厲害的冒險者來挑戰
…the sentient guardian.
擁有自我意識的守護者
Welcome
歡迎你們來到我的迷宮
I am the guardian of this labyrinth…
我就是這個迷宮的守護者
Marius.
瑪里烏斯
I heard the guardian was on the fifth floor.
我聽說守護者之前是在第五層
Well, considering my formidable opponents, I figured I should wait for you
畢竟要跟這麼厲害的強者戰鬥
This floor is my domain.
因為這層才是我的領地
Anyway,
總之你們很快就會知道
what I'm capable of.
我的真本事如何了
What's with this power? My arm feels like it's about to break.
這股威力是怎麼回事？
It's impressive that you could block that attack.
真虧你可以擋下這一招
It seems waiting was worthwhile.
看來等待是有價值的
Marius,
瑪里烏斯
I didn't come here to fight you.
我來這裡不是為了跟你戰鬥
Let's talk…
我們談談…
Exchanging blows with blades is
用刀互相交鋒
the way men converse.
這才是男人和男人的對話方式
He'll get us the second we drop our guard.
一不留神就會被他幹掉
Leave the negotiations for later.
之後再跟他交涉
Prepare for battle!
開戰吧！
Here we go!
要上囉！
What's with him?
那傢伙是怎樣 難道他背後有長眼睛嗎？
Excellent teamwork.
真是出色的團隊合作
Looks like I'll have to get serious.
看來果然還是 得拿出真本事跟你們戰鬥
Once I reveal my true abilities, I'll turn into a complete monster.
一旦動真格，我就會完全變成魔物
If you don't want to die, use your skills to escape.
不想死的話，就用技能逃走吧
Let's see if you can defeat me.
讓我看看你們是否能打敗我！
What's this guy's deal?
這傢伙是怎麼回事啊？
You can tell how dangerous he is just by the sound of his roar.
光聽他的吼叫聲
But,
但是…
I can't back down.
我不能就這麼撤回去
I'll just have to defeat him.
只能戰勝他了！
Such a heavy blow.
好沉重的攻擊
Lilia, get on my wind.
姊姊，站到我的風上
All right.
好
Mister Rud, let's take turns drawing the enemy's attention.
路德先生
I'm counting on you.
拜託你了
Magic. Taunt.
魔法，挑釁
He is insanely powerful.
雖然我有想過他的力量可能異常強大
One more blow like this
但是再吃上一擊
could be fatal.
可能就會造成致命傷
Don't take his attacks head-on.
不要正面接下他的攻擊
That's something only you can do, Mister Rud.
那種事只有路德先生辦得到啊
Nin, focus on healing.
妮恩，麻煩你專心進行回復
Lily, use support magic to maintain the vanguard's strength.
莉莉用輔助魔法維持前衛的戰力
Luna, cover us.
露娜負責掩護
Understood.
我知道了
Shugor,
修格爾，換我來吧
Taunt!
挑釁！
It's going to be a long fight.
看來必須打一場長期戰了
Then it's a battle of stamina.
那就得靠體力一決勝負了
Is that okay?
這樣沒問題嗎？
It might not be favorable for a typical party,
對一般隊伍來說不太有利
but we have Rud.
但我們這邊有路德
With Sacrificial Shield,
不僅能透過犧牲之盾
we can channel all the damage we received onto Rud.
將傷害全都聚集到路德身上
The shield force worn down in the prolonged battle
而且在長期戰中損耗的護盾
can unleash tremendous power through Life Conversion.
還能透過生命轉換發揮出超強的力量
We pin our hopes on that one strike
要將一切寄託在那一擊上
and get through the battle of endurance.
我們得撐過這場長期戰
Lady Lilia!
莉莉亞大人
At this rate,
這樣下去，早晚會有人倒下的
Luna.
露娜
As the rearguard, it's hard to watch your comrades suffer.
身為後衛，只能看著同伴受苦
But so long as we still stand, so will our vanguard.
不過只要我們還沒倒下 前衛就不會有事
So, remember this.
所以你要記住一件事
We must hold our ground and stand firm.
我們必須比任何人都努力忍著 並且堅持下去
I understand.
我知道了
He is slowing down.
他的動作變緩慢了
Is he getting tired?
是累了嗎？
We've currently used up 30,000 shield force points.
目前護盾損耗了三萬
If I hit him with that…
如果用這擊對付他的話…
Master!
主人！
I can't let this opportunity slip away. Let's finish this battle!
不能放過這個機會 用這擊一決勝負吧
Life Conversion!
生命轉換！
Did we get him?
打倒了嗎？
No way! He's still moving!
不會吧，他居然還能動！
The attack was effective.
攻擊是有效果的
If we can use Life Conversion again…
如果能再使出一次生命轉換的話…
Is everyone all right?
大家還好吧？
I'm fine.
我沒事
Lily!
莉莉！
Are you all right?
你沒事吧？
I just need a moment…
馬上就會回復了
Shugor!
修格爾！
I… I'm fine.
我沒事
I can still fight.
我還可以戰鬥
Do I really want to endanger everyone for my own selfish desires?
真的要為了自己的私欲
I don't want everyone
我不希望大家…
to risk
為了我…
their lives for me.
賭上性命
Emergency retreat.
緊急撤退！
Prepare to leave.
準備離開迷宮！
What are you saying?
你在說什麼啊？
I am the leader of this party.
我是這支隊伍的隊長
I must make the right decision.
必須做出正確的判斷！
Rud.
路德！
We've all come this far. Are you going to give up on your dreams?
都來到這裡了 你卻要放棄自己的夢想嗎？
Nin…
妮恩
Didn't I tell you to do what you want, and stop holding back?
我不是叫你 想做什麼就做，不要忍耐嗎？
Mister Rud, please don't underestimate me.
路德先生，請你不要小看我
Did you want to retreat because you saw me struggle just now?
你是看到我剛才那樣才想撤退的吧？
I came here prepared to fight,
在來到這裡時
even if it meant risking my life.
我就已經做好賭上性命戰鬥的覺悟了
Rud!
路德！
Things like running away…
逃跑什麼的
Don't give me such a lame speech!
不要說那麼沒出息的話啊！
I…
我…
I want to save Manicia.
我想拯救瑪妮西婭
So… please,
所以…
lend me your strength!
拜託大家了！
-Skill. Fusion.
-技能，融合
Fusion complete. Lilialy.
融合完畢，莉莉亞莉
Lilialy.
莉莉亞莉
Leave it to us.
交給我吧
Shugor…
修格爾
Luna… Nin…
露娜、妮恩
This time…
這次一定要…
Shugor's shield force broke!
修格爾的護盾耗盡了！
Life Conversion!
生命轉換！
If I take this blow,
如果接下這一擊
my shield force will run out, too.
我的護盾應該也會耗盡吧
But I will take it.
但我還是要接下！
I'll turn every last damage
將我最後的傷害
into power!
轉化為力量！
-Get him!
-上啊！
Life Conversion!
生命轉換！
I had fun, Rud.
我打得很高興喔，路德
I'm so tired I can't even move a finger. Now, you can do whatever you want with me.
我已經累到一根手指都動不了了
Is this the end?
這樣就結束了嗎？
Yes.
是啊
But,
不過呢
it won't be over until you give me a final blow.
你如果不給我最後一擊 就不算完全結束喔
Didn't I say at the beginning?
我一開始不是說了嗎？
I came here to negotiate with you.
我是來跟你交涉的
Marius,
瑪里烏斯
do you have the labyrinth treasure that can grant any wish?
你有可以實現 任何願望的迷宮祕寶嗎？
What? Do you want this?
什麼？你想要這個嗎？
Take it.
給你
This is a magic stone that can perform miracles.
這是可以實現奇蹟的魔石
Just hold the magic stone, imbue it with magic, and make a wish.
只要拿著那塊魔石 注入魔力再許願就可以了
But it's only good for one wish.
不過只要用過一次就會碎掉
So, use it wisely.
記得珍惜使用
Is that all?
這樣就可以了吧？
Give me the final blow.
給我最後一擊吧
No, I want to avoid the labyrinth disappearing
不，我想避免讓迷宮消失
because there's a town nearby.
因為這附近有一座城鎮
That's why,
所以…
Marius, I want you to continue to be
瑪里烏斯
In other words,
也就是說，你想跟我合作嗎？
I enjoy battling powerful individuals,
我喜歡跟強大的人戰鬥
so…
所以說呢
I'll gladly help.
我很樂意幫助你
And I hope to battle you again someday.
而且我也希望有天 可以再跟你交手一次
About that… Maybe cut me some slack.
關於這點，還請你放過我
Big Brother! You're battered and bruised all over.
哥哥！你怎麼搞得全身傷痕累累的？
I'm fine.
我沒事
Anyway, this is for you.
先不說這個了，這是要給你的
Please accept it.
你收下吧
It's the magic stone I've been searching for.
-是我一直在尋找的魔石 -什麼？
You should use it for yourself.
請哥哥為自己使用吧
Even if I use it, the result will be the same.
就算我來用，結果也是一樣
So…
所以…
Please use it.
收下吧
Big Brother…
哥哥
I understand.
我知道了
O' magic stone that grants miracles,
可以實現奇蹟的魔石啊
please fulfill this long-standing wish
請實現我長久以來的…
of mine…
心願吧
Any changes?
有什麼變化嗎？
Manicia?
瑪妮西婭？
Though it's just a bit, I don't feel as exhausted as before.
雖然只有一點點
Before, if I moved like this,
之前如果像這樣活動
I'd be out of breath in no time.
馬上就會喘不過氣
Now,
現在好像可以一直這樣轉下去
It's the first time I've seen Manicia like this.
我還是第一次看到這樣的瑪妮西婭
So long as I keep adventuring,
只要繼續冒險下去
one day, she will be completely cured.
總有一天肯定能完全治好的
Big Brother…
哥哥
I've always worried
我一直很擔心你會不會有天突然去世
But it's going to be all right now…
現在應該可以放心了吧
Every effort I've made was
至今以來我做的選擇
not in vain.
果然是正確的！
Thank you,
哥哥
Big Brother.
謝謝你
Rud!
路德
Marius?
瑪里烏斯，你怎麼過來了？
Congratulations.
恭喜你
Starting today, you're the guardian of the labyrinth.
從今天開始
What?
什麼？